Register of the Matook Raymond Nissim papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Matook Raymond Nissim papers
1922-2000
98041
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, identification documents, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, and sound and video recordings relating to the Jewish community in Shanghai from the 1920s to the 1940s.
Nissim, Matook Raymond, 1923-
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all video recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. For access to sound recordings during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
British resident of Shanghai, China.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, identification documents, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, and sound and video recordings relating to the Jewish community in Shanghai from the 1920s to the 1940s.
Jews--China.; British--China.; Shanghai (China); Video tapes.
- Biographical File, 1922-2000
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes personal material relating to the life of Matook Raymond Nissim and the lives of his parents, Nissim Marcus Matook Nissim and Flora Nissim (née Reubens).
  - Wedding certificates, 1922-1935 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes the wedding certificate of Matook Raymond Nissim's parents.
  - Birth certificates, 1929-1950 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Includes the birth certificate of Nissim Marcus Matook Nissim.
  - Matook Rahamim Nissim: An Oral History, transcript, 2000 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Note
    See also: Audiovisual Material, for video and sound cassettes of the oral history interview.
  - Passports, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Includes the passports of Matook Raymond Nissim's parents.
  - Hakol, 1949 Autumn (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Photocopy of the Shanghai Jewish School's publication.
  - Nissim Marcus Matook Nissim's certificates, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Clipping, Jewish Bulletin, 1998 October 30 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Chronology, 1999 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Ketubah, undated (Map case)
- Correspondence, 1923-1997
  - E. D. Sassoon & Co., 1946 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Family, 1923-1997 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Photographs, 1930-1990
  - Wedding of Nissim Marcus Matook Nissim and Flora Nissim, 1929 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Childhood, 1924-1939 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Relatives, 1905-1940 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Flora Nissim, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Family portrait, 1940s (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Matook Nissim, 1990s (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Yangchow, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    Includes photos of Nissim Marcus Matook Nissim during his time at Yangchow Camp "C," a Japanese internment camp outside of Shanghai, during World War II.
- Printed Matter, 1927-1998
  - Clippings, 1927-1998
    - Jews in China, 1984-1998 (Box-folder 1: 18)
      Includes material from various publications, such as The Jerusalem Post, The Wall Street Journal, Haddasah, and The Jewish World, relating to the Jewish community and individuals in China. Includes an article in Hebrew.
    - Shanghai Jewish community, 1927-1992 (Box-folder 1: 19)
      Includes material from various publications, such as Shavat, The Shanghai Times, Israel's Messenger, and The Jerusalem Post, relating to the Jewish community and individuals in Shanghai, most prominently during World War II.
    - Yangchow Japanese internment camp in Shanghai, 1970-1998 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Israel's Messenger, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    Bound copy of the periodical.
- Audiovisual Material, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Two videocassettes (VHS), circa 1998
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 98041_v_0005524
    Contains an interview of Nissim conducted by his grandson. The tapes are labeled "Tape 1 - 2hr Interview" and "Tape 2 - Dad's Copy (with photos)," respectively.
  - One compact sound cassette, 1998 September 16
    Contains audio of Nissim's oral history.